James D. Horan Papers
James D. Horan Papers
1942-1967
Horan, James David, 1914-
4.5 linear ft.
Papers of the American author, novelist. Collection contains book manuscripts, including drafts and revisions; and material relating to television productions based on Horan's work (1958-1960).
149060
Biographical History
James D. Horan (1914-) was an American newspaper editor, author and novelist. Born in New York City, he studied at Drake College in Jersey City and at the New York University Writing Center. He wrote more then 15 books, primarily history or historical fiction, and was employed as Special Events Editor for the New York Journal American for many years. He was the recipient of numerous awards for his books, and a member of many organizations of writers and historians.
He and his wife, Gertrude Dorrity, had four children.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The James D. Horan Papers consist primarily of drafts and manuscripts of his books and television work. There is a very small amount of Correspondence (two items). Manuscripts with the most amount of material in the collection include The King's Rebel, The Great American West, The Right Image, The Shadow Catcher and others. Television productions represented include The Black Cat, The D.A.'s Man, and Turnpike.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is arranged alphabetically by title. Within this, material is roughly chronological, in an attempt to demonstrate the development of an idea into a final product.
Subject and Genre Headings
Historians; Literature -- American Fiction; Popular culture; Radio, television, film; Horan, James David, 1914-; Authors, American.; Novelists, American.; Popular literature -- United States.; Television scripts.; Manuscripts for publication.; Scripts (documents); Authors.; Novelists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Incoming
    - Torgerson, Major Harry L., 1944 (Box 1)
  - Outgoing
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  - Books
    - Action To-night, 1942 (Box 1)
    - The Desperate Men, revised, 1962; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - The Great American West
      - First draft, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - Credit pages, 3 copies (Box 1)
      - Galley proofs, incomplete (Box 5)
      - Research material (Box 1)
    - The King's Rebel
      - Original drafts, 1950 (Box 2)
      - Early draft, circa 1950; 4 folders (Box 2)
      - Extra pages (Box 2)
      - Final version, books 1, 2, 3, 1953; 5 folders (Box 3)
      - With editorial comments by Ray Fadden, 1951 (Box 4)
    - The Right Image
      - Corrected typescript, pp. 1-535, 4 folders (Box 6)
      - Corrected typescript, pp. 536-848, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Page proofs, author's marked set, Feb. 17, 1967 (Box 7)
    - The Shadow Catcher, 1961
      - Books 1 and 2, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Books 3, 4, 5, 3 folders (Box 5)
      - Work sheets (Box 5)
- Television productions
  - The Black Cat
    - Carbon copies of story lines, Feb. 10, 1959; undated (Box 8)
    - Correspondence and notes re scripts, 1959 (Box 8)
    - Final scripts
      - Letter to a Little Girl, Dec. 31, 1958 (Box 8)
      - Father's Boy, Feb. 27, 1959 (Box 8)
      - The Fiend of Thornton Beach, Mar. 18, 1959 (Box 8)
      - The Seagull, Mar. 25, 1959 (Box 8)
    - Final shooting scripts
      - Pursuit of Happiness, Mar. 3, 1959 (Box 8)
    - Drafts
      - The Last Marshall, undated; 1st rough draft of storyline (typescript); 2nd draft broken down in scenes; final shooting draft (Box 8)
  - The D. A.'s Man
    - Original corrected typescript notes for two stories, undated (Box 8)
    - Two final shooting scripts and one Pete Kelley's Blues script sent by Jack Webb, 1958 (Box 8)
    - Shooting script, revised final for Inside Track, Dec. 8, 1958 (Box 8)
    - Shooting script, final for Mr. Santa Claus, Dec. 9, 1958 (Box 8)
    - Office memo re Iron Star story, Jan. 30, 1959 (Box 8)
    - Publicity, 1957-1960; undated (Box 8)
  - Turnpike
    - Series idea, undated; holograph notes, corrected typescript and final copy (Box 9)
    - Shooting schedule, holograph notes and shooting script with corrections, Mar. 2, 1960 (Box 9)
    - Stories, May 6, 1960; undated; lists, carbon copies and one script (Brother and Sister) (Box 9)
    - Pilot script (The Game), Mar. 14-18, 1960 (Box 9)
    - Budget, roster, shooting script and cast list for pilot show, Mar. 11-16, 1960 (Box 9)
    - Format presentation and typescript of pilot story (Last Call), undated (Box 9)
    - Xerox copy of original rough draft of The Toy Duck, sent to New Jersey state police for comments, undated (Box 9)
    - Publicity, 1960 (Box 9)